Kṛṣṇa is not alone.
Kṛṣṇa does not live in isolation
or in a vacuum.
[Vacuum? Krishna Is not Alone]
And it’s not a full conception of Kṛṣṇa—
to conceive of Him alone.
Sometimes Guru Mahārāj
will say,
“In the famous Gita śloka:
bahūnāṁ janmanām ante
jñānavān māṁ prapadyate
vāsudevaḥ sarvam iti
sa mahātmā su-durlabhaḥ
[Bg: 7.19]
it is saying,
‘After many, many births
a rare mahātmā may come along
who realizes: vāsudevaḥ sarvam iti—
Kṛṣṇa is everything,
He is the source of everything;
everything comes from Kṛṣṇa,
and Kṛṣṇa is everything.’”
But Guru Mahārāj said,
“That’s the beginning
of the first personal conception
in the Brahman world, the Brahmā world,
first personal conception,
but where is His potency,
His counterpart, His sweet self?”
So, Guru Mahārāj would say,
“Conceiving of Kṛṣṇa alone,
as implied in this śloka,
means Kṛṣṇa conception
at a distance.”
Sometimes we hear
of Mirabai in India.
Everyone in India
is enamoured by Mirabai,
“She is such a great devotee
and devoted from her childhood,
and writing so many songs
mad with praise of Kṛṣṇa.”
But Śrīla Guru Mahārāj
will point out
for the sake of analysis
and our benefit—
we need to understand
progressive theism—
he would say, “Well, Bhakti Vinod Ṭhākur,
Saraswatī Ṭhākur and those in their line
do not recognise her
as a substantial devotee of Kṛṣṇa.
Not saying ‘not a devotee of Kṛṣṇa’,
but as a substantial devotee of Kṛṣṇa.”
And people say, “Why?
Her songs are full
of mad praise of Kṛṣṇa.
So many songs:
Mira and Kṛṣṇa.
She is always writing songs
about Mira and Kṛṣṇa.”
And that’s the point:
her and Kṛṣṇa.
Not the āśraya-vigraha, not Rādhārāṇī,
not Lalitā–Viśākhā,
not Rūpa–Rati,
but Mira and Kṛṣṇa.
So, in as much as those,
who are near and dear to Kṛṣṇa
have been bypassed
or eliminated, or not recognized
by the ontological
method of measurement
it means this is a distant
Kṛṣṇa conception
for where can Kṛṣṇa be seen alone,
but at a great distance,
far from the Absolute centre;
not the extreme,
not the golden mean.
‘Golden mean’ means
the aprākṛta‒līla of Kṛṣṇa—
Goloka Vṛndāvan, where
there is Rādhā and Kṛṣṇa,
Lalitā–Viśākhā, Rupa–Rati,
Subal–Sridam,
Nanda–Yaśodā, gopa–gopī,
etc.
So, Kṛṣṇa is worshipped
along with His paraphernalia—
those who are dear to Kṛṣṇa.